"Ms. Suenaga.
“老師
Back then I was a little crazy.
當時我的思緒十分混亂
I'd get irritated for no reason,
我無緣由地感到煩躁
and lose control.
和激動
To a point where I couldn't see myself or my surroundings.
直到完全看不見自己或周遭
That's how much…
我就是如此地…
I loved you."
喜歡妳”
I LOVED YOU
（我喜歡妳）
You're being accused of sexual misconduct.
妳被控訴做出淫穢行為的嫌疑
RESIGNATION LETTER
（辭呈）
I will quit teaching.
我會辭職
What do they mean discipline? Are you quitting?
處分是什麼意思？妳要辭職嗎？
-That was a mistake. -No.
-那樣是不對的 -不
-It was wrong. -Why?
-那是錯的 -為什麼？
Because you're fifteen!
因為你才十五歲！
Ms. Suenaga!
老師！
Hiji--
聖…
Hijiri!
小聖！
I decided my future!
我決定志願了！
I'm going to be an adult soon!
我很快會成為大人！
So don't go!
所以不要走！
Hijiri!
小聖！
"And then
“然後
you disappeared.
小聖便消失了
It was the summer when I was 15
在我十五歲的夏天
when you disappeared."
消失了”
WHEN YOU DISAPPEARED
（消失了）
How about a class reunion?
要辦同學會嗎？
We're doing a reunion?
我們辦同學會？
When?
什麼時候？
Next month?
下個月吧？
Nice, it's been like three years since we graduated junior high.
好主意，國中畢業之後 已經三年沒見了吧
Easy for you to say when you don't have exams.
九重不用考試就是說得輕鬆啊
I'm taking over our family liquor store.
我要繼承我家的酒鋪啊
I'm thinking of inviting Kuroiwa.
我想邀請黑岩
What?
什麼？
-Kuroiwa? -He may not come anyway.
-黑岩？ -他應該不會來吧
He won't.
他不會吧
He stopped coming to school.
後來也不來學校
-We didn't even graduate together. -Have you not seen him either?
-甚至沒有一起畢業 -岩崎，妳沒見到他嗎？
Nope.
沒有
Not since the fireworks. Zero explanation, zero contact.
自從煙火大會之後，零解釋，零聯絡
Absolutely nothing!
別說零了，根本是負值！
I thought we were friends.
我還以為我們是朋友
Just kidding!
開玩笑的啦！
-Not to mention Suenaga suddenly quitting. -Yeah.
-那時末永也突然辭職了 -是啊
There were lots of rumors, like she ran away with Kuroiwa.
謠言滿天飛，像是她跟黑岩私奔了
-Or Kuroiwa got her pregnant. -Or had a shotgun wedding.
-還是她懷了黑岩的孩子 -還是先有後婚
Or she got abducted by aliens!
還是被外星人抓走了！
That didn't happen.
沒有那回事
I wonder where she is now.
不知道她如今在哪裡，做什麼呢
Probably a housewife.
應該就是家庭主婦吧
Here is your fried chicken and potato salad lunch box.
久等了，這是炸雞和馬鈴薯沙拉便當
-Thanks. -Please come again.
-謝謝 -謝謝光臨
-The seaweed and chicken set. -Right away.
-海苔便當和炸雞 -好
Your change is 200 yen.
找您兩百圓
I'm off then.
那我先走了
Have a good one.
辛苦了
Welcome!
謝謝光臨
KOMIYA DAI-ICHI ELEMENTARY
（小宮第一小學）
Hijiri!
聖
That's Ms. Hijiri!
要叫我“聖老師”！
-Thank you! -My pleasure. Here.
-謝謝！ -不客氣，給你
Oh! It's from our store!
哦，是我們家的便當
Did you get forced to help again?
難道又叫妳幫忙啦？
Just a little bit.
只有一下下啦
Yuto's mother needed to go to the dentist.
悠斗的媽媽要去看牙醫
-You're so kind, Ms. Suenaga. -Let's play, Ms. Hijiri!
-末永老師妳人太好了啦 -來玩吧，聖老師！
Later, I have some work to do now.
待會再玩，老師還有工作要做
Yes!
好耶！
Now you've done it!
竟敢丟我！
Hit them over there!
丟他們那邊！
Ready?
好了嗎？
-You must be disappointed, Ms. Chizuru. -What?
-妳很失望吧，千鶴老師 -什麼？
Ms. Suenaga took your throne as queen of the campus.
學校女神的地位被末永老師搶走了
Don't be ridiculous, Nogami.
不要胡說了，野上
I got inducted in the hall of fame.
我已經進名人堂了
I passed the torch to my protégé.
是我自己離開女神寶座讓給後輩啦
I'm a generous woman.
我可是很大方的女性
You're so kind, even though you typically hate young women.
千鶴老師人真溫柔 平常明明很討厭年輕女孩
What are you talking about? I like the troubled ones.
你在說什麼呀？ 我喜歡不省心的孩子啊
Does Ms. Suenaga have a boyfriend?
末永老師有男友嗎？
There it is! You've asked a hundred times.
又來了！你問第一百次了
No.
才沒有
Maybe twice.
好像才第二次
Oh, yes. You're not interested at all.
是啦，你完全沒那個意思
Come on, Hijiri!
快點，聖！
It's Ms. Hijiri!
是“聖老師”！
It's so nice we got a good teacher.
幸好是來了一位好老師
Throw it!
快丟吧！
She's great with the kids.
她很會逗孩子
She used to teach junior high.
之前好像是國中老師
She came here after her engagement fell through?
聽說是婚事告吹才跑到這裡來呀？
So Ms. Suenaga has some baggage?
這麼說，末永老師也是另有故事嗎？
Well, I wouldn't know.
這我也不曉得
Really?
是嗎？
Why did her engagement fall through?
她為什麼沒結成婚呢？
What happened?
發生了什麼事？
I need to lock up the gym!
我得要去鎖體育館了！
I forgot!
我忘了！
Catch it, Yuto!
接球，悠斗！
Ow.
好痛
Tachibana!
橘同學
You okay?
沒事吧？
That must hurt.
很痛吧？
Are you okay?
還好嗎？
Just a little scrape, you're all okay now.
只是稍微擦傷，已經沒事了
Thank you.
謝謝妳
Were you in the library again today?
橘同學，妳今天也去圖書館了嗎？
I love this book too.
老師也喜歡這本書
The cat is so cute.
這個貓咪很可愛吧
Do you like it, too?
橘同學，妳也喜歡嗎？
Please! You need to stop annoying me.
拜託妳不要再煩我了！
Mosquito.
蚊子
What? Mosquito?
什麼？蚊子？
Oh, my!
哦，真的耶
That was a good catch!
妳打得真準
You caught me by surprise.
妳嚇了我一跳
Thank you.
謝謝妳
-Can I see you, Ms. Hijiri? -Okay.
-聖老師，可以見妳一下嗎？ -好的
To her home?
去她家？
Her mom should be home. Would you mind walking Tachibana home?
她母親應該在家 妳能送橘同學回家嗎？
Of course, I'll need to explain her injury anyway.
沒問題，也要跟她說受傷的事情
That's part of it, but she hasn't turned in the field trip fee yet.
除了這件事，她還沒繳遠足費用
Could you collect it?
妳也順便收一下？
-Yes. -Also.
-好 -還有
I haven't seen her mother around lately.
最近都沒看到那個媽媽
Check on her for me.
也麻煩妳去看看怎麼回事
Understood.
我知道了
Here?
是這裡嗎？
Mom.
媽媽
Hello.
妳好
Ms. Suenaga, thank you so much.
老師，抱歉，勞煩妳跑一趟
-So today, Ayano-- -I heard she fell!
-今天彩乃她… -我有聽說她跌倒了
Thank you.
謝謝
Also, there's a field trip--
還有不好意思，遠足的…
Right, the payment.
對了，遠足費用
-I'll send it with her tomorrow. -Okay.
-明天就讓她一起帶去 -好
-Sorry, goodbye. -Goodbye.
-抱歉，再見 -好的
-Welcome home. -Thanks.
-歡迎回家 -我回來了
She sent you away?
馬上就被趕回來了？
Yes, it seems she had a guest over.
是的，她好像有客人
She said she would send the payment tomorrow.
說遠足費用明天會給
So the rumors were true.
那傳言果然是真的
-Huh? -She's got a man or something?
-嗯？ -聽說她有男人還是什麼的事？
But she's a single mother, she's free to find romance.
不過她是單親媽媽，可以自由戀愛吧
Still, I hear men are constantly coming and going.
可是聽說她男性關係很亂哦
Her family is a bit complicated.
她們家有點複雜
Complicated?
複雜？
You didn't know?
妳不知道嗎？
The Tachibanas are big landowners.
橘家是這附近的大地主
But Ms. Miwa, that's Ayano's mother--
可是美和小姐，就是彩乃的媽媽…
She graduated from here.
她是從我們這裡畢業的
She cheated on her husband with his best friend.
她跟老公的好友外遇
-It was forbidden love. -That's right.
-就是所謂的禁忌之戀 -對啊
They knew it was wrong, but I bet they just lost control.
可就算他們知道是錯的 他們還是會情不自禁啊
-It must have been hard. -She got divorced.
-一定很辛苦吧 -結果她離了婚
And moved into an old family property to raise Ayano alone.
搬進老家的空屋，獨自養育彩乃
How shameful.
沒臉見人
-It's a small town. -Rumors get around quick.
-畢竟這是個小鎮啊 -一旦傳出謠言，就一發不可收拾了
Once out, it's curtains.
一傳出來就徹底完蛋
Heaven forbid.
老天保佑
-Ah, shoot. -Are you okay, Hijiri?
-啊，糟了 -沒事吧，聖？
I'm sorry.
抱歉
I'm heading home.
我要回去了
See you soon.
再見
-Bye. -Be careful.
-再見 -路上小心
It was forbidden love.
就是所謂的禁忌之戀
How dare you use my Akira as some play thing!
憑什麼利用我家阿晶當妳的玩物？
Who do you think you are!
妳以為妳是誰！
I had to…
我要…
quit the school.
辭職了
I fell for a student.
我喜歡上學生了
Rumors get around quick.
一旦傳出謠言，就一發不可收拾了
MACHIGURA CITY MARKET
（町倉市雜貨市集）
-I'd like this. -Okay.
-我要這個 -好的
I'm so glad I could buy the same one.
幸好能買到同樣的杯子
I was sure he said it was bought here.
我記得他說去年是在這裡買的
The principal is away today, so you can replace it without him knowing.
校長今天出差 趁現在買一個偷偷放回去
Sorry to make you come with me.
抱歉，還讓你陪我來
Please, you're always helping me as my assistant teacher.
哪裡，妳身為副班導幫了我很多忙
Sorry.
對不起
-I'm sorry. -It's okay.
-對不起 -沒關係
I wanted this book.
這是我很想要的書
This looks useful for class.
這個好像能用來教課
They're cheap, we should buy a few.
反正很便宜，不如買幾本回去吧
Let's.
就這麼辦
AUTUMN READING
（秋天的讀物）
You picked a good one!
你挑了個好的！
-Take your time. -Okay.
-慢慢看哦 -好的
It's almost cherry blossom season.
櫻花就快要開了
Yes.
是
Not bad, right, Ms. Suenaga?
不錯吧，末永老師？
Ms. Suenaga?
末永老師？
Once an offender, always an offender.
曾犯過錯的人一定會重蹈覆轍
What happened three years ago?
三年前發生什麼事？
Suenaga? Who's that again?
末永？誰啊？
I'm interested in you.
我很在意這樣的妳
What if they find out and it ruins the life I have now.
怎麼辦？萬一他們知道的話 現在的生活就全完了
Hold on.
等一下
-Something wrong? -What?
-怎麼啦？ -什麼？
I just wanted to look over here too.
只是也想看看這邊的東西
Oh!
哦！
These are cute too.
這個也好可愛哦
Yeah.
是啊
That's nice.
這個不錯呢
-We could decorate our office. -Yes.
-我們可以裝飾教職員室 -是啊
-Look! -That's huge.
-妳看這個！ -好大一個哦
I wonder how many would fit. We could give everyone one.
能放多少個？可以每人給一個
We could all pitch in.
大家可以參與
Hey, Akira.
阿晶，久等了
Look at the treasure I found!
看看我挖到的寶！
I saw something Sayuri would like.
那邊有小百合奶奶感覺會喜歡的東西
Was it jewelry?
是什麼？飾品嗎？
Sayuri likes emerald green, right?
小百合奶奶喜歡翠綠色，對吧？
Yeah, she likes emerald green.
是啊，她喜歡翠綠色
Shall we get going?
要走了嗎？
Sure.
好
Because you're fifteen!
因為你才十五歲！
I'm going to be an adult soon!
我很快會成為大人！
Akira?
阿晶嗎？
How's he been lately?
他最近怎麼樣？
You have nothing to worry about.
妳不用擔心
Every day, he wakes up early
他每天都很早起
to do his workbooks,
早上起床就寫參考書
and goes back to studying when he comes home.
從學校回來就繼續念書
Thank you for taking care of him, Mother.
實在是承蒙妳關照了，媽媽
Akira, I got a birthday card.
阿晶，這是生日卡
-Write something. -Okay.
-你寫一下 -好的
Your mom's here.
你媽媽來了
Your place is close to his school,
從妳這裡去學校也比較近
and because you and Joffe are looking after him,
因為平常有喬飛跟妳照顧他
he was able to settle down.
他才能安定下來好好生活
Here.
來
That reminds me.
對了
Here is this month's room and board.
這是這個月份的寄宿費
And this is for your birthday.
還有這個是妳的生日禮物
Happy birthday.
生日快樂
You all have been so lovely today.
真開心，今天大家都很親切啊
Don't worry, he'll come around soon.
總有一天會一起笑著聊天的
I should get going.
那我差不多該回去了
Do you have a second?
社長，可以借一步說話嗎？
-You saw her? -At the market in Machigura.
-你看到她了？ -在町倉市的雜貨市集
It was really her and not just a look alike?
真的是她？不是長得像的人嗎？
It was definitely her.
絕對是她
I almost shouted in surprise.
我嚇了一跳，差點叫出聲音
Did Akira notice her?
阿晶有發現她嗎？
No, but it was a close one.
沒有，好像剛好擦身而過
It's been three years now.
自那以後已經過了三年了
I'll never let you meet her again.
我不會再讓你和她見面
This isn't okay.
這是不對的
I don't care what you say.
我不管妳說什麼
I'll marry her one day!
我以後要跟老師結婚！
Have you lost your mind!
你瘋了吧！
That summer,
那個夏天
I ripped them apart
我拼命將他們分開
to get my little boy back.
讓他變回普通的孩子
But now he hates me,
結果現在被他討厭
and won't even see me.
甚至連我都不見
I'm sure he's just mixed up emotionally.
肯定是一時腦袋太混亂了
You'll get there eventually.
總會恢復的
His exams are coming up.
他就快要考試了
Then off to college.
然後就要過大學生活
He'll probably live on his own, get a part-time job,
應該會一個人生活、打工
and get his driver's license.
去考駕照
If he just grows up a little year by year,
如果能像這樣一年年長大
I'll be happy.
那我就滿足了
How was she?
她怎麼了？
She seemed well.
看起來很好
She was with a guy.
旁邊好像有個男人
Maybe she got married.
也許結婚了吧
She had a fiancé, didn't she?
我記得她有未婚夫，不是嗎？
To be perfectly honest, this contract is totally unnecessary.
老實說，我覺得完全不需要這份合約
We would increase our share by staying the course.
照現在這樣 也會增加我們的市場佔有率
We don't have a choice.
我們也沒得選啊
If you abandon our partner for short-term profits,
如果要因眼前的利益拋棄合作夥伴
then I quit!
那我辭職！
Hold on.
等一下
Kawai!
川合
You're quitting?
你要辭職啊？
What now?
怎麼了？
Good question.
問得好
Want to mull it over together over dinner?
晚上一邊吃飯一邊想吧？
Sounds good.
好啊
Chief wants to see you first.
在此之前，部長在找你
The chief?
部長？
You're quitting?
你要辭職嗎？
Chief Haraguchi.
原口部長
Today's your first day?
是今天第一天上任嗎？
Welcome to Tokyo HQ.
歡迎來到東京總公司
So my first day as chief, and I hear you want to resign.
才剛上任就聽說你要辭職
Well, denied.
駁回
Don't be so flippant.
別說蠢話了
But Asia Heavy Industries--
可是亞洲重工…
I will look over it myself.
我會重新審查
Do you trust me?
能信任我嗎？
Well,
那…
okay.
好吧
Thank God.
太好了
Honestly, I was a little scared.
老實說，我有點害怕
What are you doing?
你在幹嘛啊？
When did you get so hot-headed anyway?
你什麼時候變得這麼衝動？
Oh, from that.
哦，是那件事啊
Three years ago, your fiancé H broke off the engagement.
三年前，你的未婚妻H小姐逃了婚
You mean, Hijiri.
是聖啦
Ever since, you threw yourself in work, becoming hardened.
在那之後 你埋頭工作，腦筋都變死板啦
Thank you for letting me vent then.
謝謝妳當時聽我發洩
Three years since then,
那之後過了三年
H was 25, now 28.
當時25歲的H小姐已經28歲
And the middle schooler
只是國中生的他
could be eligible to vote.
搞不好也有投票權了
I don't really care.
那不關我的事
That's what I mean, Kawai.
你就是這樣，川合
-Hijiri. -Yes?
-聖 -是
-Open up. -Coming.
-開門 -來了
There we go.
來
I went pear picking with the hubby.
我跟老公去采梨子了
-Really? -Take what you want.
-是嗎？ -妳拿喜歡的去吧
Really?
可以嗎？
Thank you!
謝謝妳！
-Just one? -That's all I need since I'm on my own.
-只拿一個嗎？ -這樣就夠啦，我一個人吃不完啦
You're kidding me.
騙人的吧？真是的
-Heave-ho. -Do you want to join me?
-嗨喲 -要不要一起吃飯？
Thanks.
謝啦
That's all you're eating?
妳只吃這些啊？
You used to eat three helpings on your own.
妳不是向來都連吃三個回合嗎？
No, I didn't.
沒有，我才沒有
Maybe two.
只吃兩個回合啦
Thank you for this meal.
我開動了
Something happen?
發生什麼事了？
I think I boiled them too long.
好像煮太久了
Hijiri, you promised to share if something happens.
聖，說好了不能隱瞞
Today
今天
I saw him.
我看到他了
Who?
誰？
You're joking.
不會吧？
But I mean, it was just a glance from far away.
我是說，只是遠遠瞥到一眼
He didn't notice at all.
他完全沒注意到我
Do you want egg?
妳要蛋嗎？
How was he?
他看起來怎麼樣？
I was relieved to see he was well.
看起來過得不錯，我放心了
That's it?
就這樣？
When I saw him,
我看著他
it reminded me of three years ago.
令我想起三年前的事
When I had nowhere to go, I went to my parents' first.
我當時無處可去，一開始先回老家
-I'll do that. -You don't have to.
-我來吧 -不用啦
Just let me.
讓我來吧
Go answer it.
妳去開門吧
Neither my mom or dad said anything, just took me in.
爸媽什麼都沒說，只是默默地接受我
Is Hijiri here?
小聖回來啦？
She's staying with us after she quit the school.
是啊，她辭職了，現在留在家裡
Is that so?
是這樣啊？
She had some health issues.
她身體不太舒服
I'm sorry to hear that.
真是辛苦
I knew something had to change after I overheard her.
聽到那些話，我覺得不能再這樣下去
Making your parents lie means you have them worried.
害父母必須說謊 就代表我讓他們擔心了
That's right, Hijiri.
沒錯，聖
So I started working at a cram school.
後來開始在補習班打工當講師
…is your answer.
…就是答案
-You got them all right! -Yes!
-好厲害，全對呢！ -好耶！
-I got it, too! -You did?
-我也做完了 -妳做完了嗎？
You searched hard for something you could do,
像那樣拼命找自己能做的事
but it was clear you still had a longing to teach,
我就是深深體會到 妳仍然很想當老師的心願
so when there was an opening at my school, I called you.
所以現在的學校有職缺時 我便告訴了妳
I can't be grateful enough.
實在是感激不盡
Plus I got a letter.
而且我也收到了信
Letter?
信？
When I talked to the principal, we reached out to Koboshi Junior High
我和校長談過之後，聯絡子星中學
and spoke to a Ms. Shioya.
就在那時和鹽谷老師聯絡了
I wish
我原本希望
I could've taught her more.
能更用心培養她的
She wrote a letter for you.
她特地為妳寫了一封信
How she was continuing to root for you,
她說會為妳加油
and asked us to give you a chance.
要我們給妳一個機會
I didn't tell you so you wouldn't get complacent.
我怕說了之後妳會鬆懈 所以就沒告訴妳
When I saw him,
看到他的時候
I had an instant thought.
我馬上就想
What if they found out and it ruins the life I have now.
怎麼辦？萬一他們知道的話 現在的生活就全完了
Next thing I know,
等我回神
I had distanced myself.
我已經離開了
I ran away.
我跑開了
I just want to get recertified in Tokyo
我只想在東京 重新得到教師甄試的機會
and live on as a teacher here.
希望能夠一直在這裡當老師
That's all I want now.
這就是我現在的心願
I want to settle down and work hard here.
我想在這裡安定下來，好好努力
I know that.
我知道
Don't worry, that stuff won't happen again.
放心，不會再發生那樣的事了
Still, Hijiri, you need to stop wallowing and find yourself a good man.
不過啊，妳不要一直這麼消沉 妳也該找個新對象了
What about Mr. Nogami?
妳覺得野上老師怎麼樣？
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Nogami may seem careless, but he has his act together.
野上看起來很糊塗，其實人很可靠
I always thought you two would make a good couple.
我之前就覺得你們也許很適合
Yeah, right.
又來了
Listen, Hijiri, if you want to take teaching seriously,
聽著，聖 如果妳真的想一直當老師的話
settling down is part of it.
結婚安定下來是其中一個方法
No way.
不行啦…
I don't have the bandwidth right now.
我現在沒那種想法
Open up!
開門！
That voice.
那個聲音
Isn't that your husband?
是妳老公吧？
Good evening.
是，晚安
-I came to pick you up. -Thanks, Hubby.
-我來接妳了 -謝啦，老公
Look, Hijiri!
看，小聖！
-Pears! -Yes.
-梨子！ -是
I already brought her some!
我早就拿來了
-Can I come in? -Sure.
-可以進來嗎？ -當然
So you did.
真的，妳拿來了
She can't eat that much.
她吃不完那麼多啦
-I can share them at work. -And Micchan.
-那拿去學校發吧 -還可以拿給小美
Right, Micchan!
對哦，小美
Micchan is the type who would eat pears instead of drinking water.
小美她都不喝水，都靠梨子補充水分
-Really? -Let's give her lots.
-真的嗎？ -多給她一點吧
KOBOSHIDAIRA JUNIOR HIGH CLASS OF 2015 REUNION
（2015年度畢業 子星中學三年一班同學會）
Hold up, I want in.
等一下…我也要…
Let me in.
我也要
MS. SHIOYA
（鹽谷老師）
-Hey, Runachi. -Yu! Long time!
-嗨，瑠奈 -小優！好久不見！
-Yay! -Kosaka.
-耶！ -香阪
-Long time no see. -Hey!
-香阪，好久不見 -嗨！
She's changed.
她變真多
All right, is this everyone?
各位，應該全員到齊了吧？
-Yeah! -Is it?
-是！ -是嗎？
Okay, shall we get started then?
好，那就開始吧？
Yeah!
好！
I'll be your host, Michiru Ebihara!
我是今天的主持人海老原滿！
Long time no see!
好久不見！
Right in the gut! You okay?
直接打下去了！你沒事吧？
You alright?
沒事吧？
You watch the super bantamweight fight yesterday?
你昨天有看超雛量級的比賽嗎？
Yeah, knocked out in the seventh.
看了，是第七回被擊倒
Hold on.
等一下…
What?
什麼？
What's with them?
他們兩個是怎麼回事？
No idea.
不知道
Was that them making up?
是說，這樣就和好啦？
I wanted to be a little more disappointed.
怎麼不讓我更加失望點
Hey, Kuroiwa!
喂，黑岩！
-Can I ask you something? -Sure.
-我可以問你一件事嗎？ -當然
What happened three years ago?
三年前發生什麼事？
Was it related to Suenaga?
果然跟末永有關嗎？
Do you still see her?
你還有跟她見面嗎？
Suenaga?
末永？
Who's that again?
誰啊？
Yeah, right!
對，就是啊！
You were so obsessed.
明明被迷得神魂顛倒
The weather report said 30 percent.
天氣預報是說機率是百分之三十
-Just make sure they have rain gear. -Good point.
-不過還是確認他們有帶雨具 -也對
If it rains, we can go to the community center and play.
假如下雨 就改到附近的里民中心玩耍
-Got it. -Unless it's just drizzling.
-好的 -除非只是毛毛雨
Right, we'll just wait and see…
是啊，那就看情況再決定…
I'll see you later then.
那麼，辛苦了
Okay.
辛苦了
-Bye! -You have to come!
-再見！ -你要來哦！
I'll walk you home.
我送妳回去
-What? -Why? You going somewhere?
-什麼？ -為什麼？你們要去哪嗎？
I want to talk to Iwasaki a bit.
我有話想跟岩崎說
Okay.
好啊
I'll text later.
再聯絡
Sure.
好
-Bye.
-再見
-Take care. -See ya.
-保重
I've always thought Kuroiwa was a jerk in sheep's clothing.
我以前就這麼覺得了 黑岩就是披著羊皮的渣男啊
That part of you hasn't changed.
你這點還是沒變
You invited me out, and don't even talk.
你約我出來卻不說話
Sorry.
對不起
I was worried when you dropped out, you know.
你突然不來學校 害我很擔心，知道嗎？
Sorry.
對不起
You also moved out without telling anyone.
沒和任何人說就搬走了
Stop apologizing.
不要一直道歉啦
Today,
今天
I'm apologizing to everyone.
我一直在跟大家道歉
Where'd you go for high school?
你高中念哪裡？
Seitoichi High.
西斗一高
Wow! That's the best school in the Prefecture!
好厲害！那是縣內的名門高中呢！
I had a lot of free time
我那時很閒
so I just spent my time studying.
所以一直念書
So,
所以
what if I told you
如果我告訴你
that I still liked you, would you be creeped out?
我還喜歡著你，你會嚇一跳嗎？
You would, right?
想必會吧？
I never thought about it.
我從沒想過
I didn't either.
我也沒有啊
To think I'd confess my love to you today.
沒想到今天還會跟你告白
For the fourth time.
而且是第四次了
-Fourth? -Yeah, four times by my count.
-第四次？ -對啊，就我所知是四次啦
I see.
是哦
Four times, huh?
四次？
Do you have someone you like now?
你現在有喜歡的人嗎？
I'm not sure.
我不知道
God, you're such a player despite who you are.
天啊，真輕浮 明明只不過是區區的黑岩
-What's that mean? -You heard me!
-什麼意思啊？ -就那意思啊！
Here, I got your address from your parents.
來，我跟妳父母問到了地址
Sorry for dropping by.
抱歉突然過來
Thank you for coming.
謝謝你過來
You could've mailed them.
你寄給我就好了嘛
It's been bothering me.
我一直很困擾
How I left things…
我最後…
I was in the wrong.
那是我不對
I said such awful things.
我對妳說了很過分的話
I can't marry you.
我沒辦法嫁給你
Then you should be alone
以後妳就變回一個人
and lose everything.
變得一無所有吧
I'm sorry.
-對不起
It took me three years to get here.
我花了三年才敢來
Honestly, it feels like
老實說，感覺
I wasn't myself back then.
那時的我仿佛不像是自己
How could I have done something so stupid?
總想著“為什麼要做這種蠢事？”
Me too.
我也是
Thinking back, I was full of pride,
現在回想起來，我實在是太傲慢
and a part of me was trying to control you.
總是想試圖掌控妳
No way.
怎麼會呢？
I should go.
那我走了
Was that guy you were with your…
剛才跟妳在一起的人是妳的…
Mr. Nogami?
你說野上老師嗎？
He's the head teacher of my class.
他是我現在負責班級的班導
He seemed nice.
感覺人不錯
It's nothing like that, I've got my own problems.
完全不是那樣啦，我現在沒那種心情
Probably time we both move on.
我想我們是時候開始新生活了
I think it's time we should face our lives and move forward.
差不多該面對許多事情，繼續前進了
So, have a good life.
所以妳要幸福
What about you?
你呢？
You have anyone?
現在有對象嗎？
Yeah.
是啊
I'm about to.
要開始找了
Good morning.
早安
Did you hear?
你聽說了嗎？
When we took a look at the long-term, Asia Heavy Industries seemed better.
長久來看，確實是亞洲重工比較好
So we extended the contract.
所以續訂了合約
No need to thank me.
不必謝我
I'm interested.
我很在意
What?
什麼？
In the contract?
合約內容嗎？
A manager who works hard,
一個工作幹練的上司
but whose voice would shake during presentations.
卻會聲音顫抖地報告
She can't hold her liquor, but listens to my rants,
明明酒量不好，卻願意聽我訴苦
and eats meat with me.
陪我一起吃肉
When I was at my lowest, she'd cheer me up,
在我身處谷底時會為我打氣
and supported me.
支持我
I'm interested in you.
我很在意這樣的妳
For some reason.
莫名地
How were the results?
成績怎麼樣？
Pretty good this time.
這次還不錯
I think it's time we face life and move forward.
差不多該面對許多事情，繼續前進了
Planetarium?
天文館嗎？
Music? Sobafurukinoko's?
音樂會？蘑菇蕎麥麵的？
-Let's all go together! -Yeah!
-我們一起去吧 -好啊
It ends this week.
到這週為止啊
I can't make it.
我不行
And I have a practice test.
我那天也要模擬考
-Really? -Akira?
-真的嗎？ -阿晶？
Long time.
好久不見
Who is this hottie?
這個美女是誰？
Congrats on your college admission.
恭喜妳考上大學
That was six months ago!
太遲了，都六個月前的事了
Too bad.
很遺憾
I got a boyfriend now.
我已經交到男友了
I'm here! Sorry you had to wait!
我到了！對不起，讓你久等了
Was that…
她難道是…
An ex?
前女友？
Don't you care about me?
你就不能對我好一點嗎？
Stop it, okay!
別鬧了！知道了啦
-Got it? -Buzz Cut.
-知道了？ -平頭
Alright.
好吧
So I guess this is out.
那這個就算了
-None of us can make it. -Yeah.
-大家時間都湊不起來 -是啊
The two of us could go.
我們兩個去吧
What? The two of us?
什麼？我們兩個人？
Yeah.
是啊
What was that?
那是怎麼樣？
You want to?
妳不是喜歡嗎？
That guy's a total wolf.
他果然是徹頭徹尾的大野狼
You sure?
你確定嗎？
That's Kuroiwa.
黑岩就是這樣
Sure.
可以啊
Then we're on.
那就這樣決定
Akira started hanging out with his old friends?
阿晶願意見以前的朋友啦？
He has.
是啊
Maybe he's finally ready to open up.
他有很多心結都化解了吧
I'm glad.
太好了
What a relief.
我放心了
I'm just worried he might hear rumors about Ms. Suenaga.
我只是擔心他會不會聽到老師的傳言
She was definitely buying something that day.
那天她確實買了些什麼
So I told the shop owner that I think I knew one of his customers.
所以我跑去問店長 我說可能認識上次買東西的客人
Then he said that
然後店長說
she's a teacher.
她是老師
Teacher?
老師？
He said they mentioned a teacher's lounge,
因為他們在討論教職員室要怎麼裝飾
so they were probably teachers at some school.
所以他們可能是某所學校的老師
She's still teaching?
難道她還在當老師嗎？
Her?
那個女的？
Okay, keep going.
好，繼續走
We're almost there.
我們就快到了
I need help, Mr. Nogami!
幫幫我，野上老師！
-Okay, I'll help you. -That's a big one!
-好，老師來幫妳 -好大顆哦！
Keep digging!
繼續挖！
Don't stop.
不要停
-That's a big one. -It's big.
-好大顆哦 -好大
This is a tough one.
這個很難拔呢
You're so lame!
老師好遜哦！
Size doesn't matter!
大小又沒關係！
Excuse me.
那個
Were you okay?
妳還好嗎？
What?
什麼？
That person we ran into,
上次遇到的人
was he your former…?
他是不是妳之前的…
Yes, we were engaged to be married.
對，是原本說要結婚的對象
He came by to see me,
他來見我
and we got to catch up.
我們久違地聊了一下
You looked well suited.
你們看起來很相配
I'm surprised you broke up.
讓人覺得你們會分手很不可思議
A lot happened.
發生很多事
Maybe I'm misunderstanding something--
也許是我誤會…
-Tachibana. -Huh?
-橘同學 -什麼？
-Her lunch… -Did you forget your lunch?
-便當… -妳忘了帶便當嗎？
What? She forgot?
騙人的吧？她忘了嗎？
You can have this.
這個給妳
You can have mine too!
我的也給妳！
Mine too.
那我的也給妳
I don't want it!
我不要！
-What are you doing? -Tachibana.
-你們在幹嘛？ -橘同學
But salmon is so good.
鮭魚很好吃啊，幹嘛這樣…
Okay, let's go.
好了，走吧
Have some more.
多吃點吧
Okay, time to go home.
好了，解散
-Goodbye! -Be careful.
-再見！ -路上小心哦
Okay, take care.
好的，保重
-Bye, Ms. Suenaga. -Bye.
-老師再見 -再見
Bye.
再見
Bye, take care now.
再見，保重
Should we talk to her mother about her lunch?
我們是不是應該 跟她母親說便當的事？
That might be good.
也是
Tachibana.
橘同學
-We dug up so many today. -Yeah.
-今天挖到很多地瓜呢 -是啊
Do you like sweet potatoes?
妳喜歡吃地瓜嗎？
Please, stop!
拜託，住手！
-Mom! -Shut up!
-媽媽！ -閉嘴！
-Is everything okay? -It's a misunderstanding!
-妳還好嗎？ -這是誤會！
No!
才不是！
Someone told me they've seen my husband come here multiple times!
有人看到我老公跑來這裡好幾次！
It's a misunderstanding.
我說了，這是誤會
-He just helped with the plumbing. -Oh, please!
-我只是請他來修水管 -開什麼玩笑！
-How dare you! -Stop!
-真不要臉！ -快住手
Please calm down!
請冷靜點！
Stay out of it!
不關妳的事！
-It's your fault! -Hey!
-都是妳的錯！ -喂！
It's all your fault!
都是妳的錯！
-Mom. -It's all your fault!
-媽媽 -都是妳的錯！
That's enough!
夠了！
There's a child here!
有小孩在看啊！
Let's calm down and talk this over.
請冷靜下來好好談談吧
This woman isn't capable of talking.
這種女人無法好好說話
You've done this before, right?
妳之前也幹過這種事，對吧？
Cheated with your husband's best friend, so he divorced you.
跟老公的好友搞婚外情，所以離婚了
Like I'd ever trust the likes of you!
誰會相信妳這種人！
The whole town
整個小鎮
knows your past.
都知道妳的過去
People don't change.
人不可能會改變
-Once an offender, always an offender. -Please stop.
-曾犯過錯的人一定會重蹈覆轍 -別說了
If my husband ever comes here again, I'll make you pay.
如果我老公又跑來這裡 我絕不放過妳
Are you okay?
妳還好嗎？
I'm used to it.
我習慣了
Let me help.
我來幫忙
Could you leave?
可以請你們回去嗎？
I'm very tired today.
我今天很累
But Ayano's lunch--
但是彩乃她的便當…
Please leave.
請回吧
Ms. Suenaga.
末永老師
We should call it a day.
我們今天就先告辭吧
Okay.
好
Bye.
再見
See you later, Tachibana.
橘同學，再見
You're not going home yet?
妳還不回家呀？
I'll be finishing up soon.
我就快做完了
Okay.
這樣啊
-I'm heading out now. -Okay.
-那我先走了 -好
See you tomorrow.
辛苦了
Um, Ms. Suenaga.
那個…末永老師
You know,
剛才
I believe the past is the past.
我覺得過去的事都過去了
That woman said she couldn't trust Tachibana's mother.
那個女人說她不相信橘同學的母親
But if you live long enough,
可是活了好幾十年
you will make mistakes.
無論是誰都曾犯錯
History, failure, regret.
過去、失敗、後悔
A society that never forgives mistakes,
一個絕不原諒失敗的社會
or one that roots for those doing their best.
還是願意替努力生活的人加油的社會
The answer becomes easy
我們想讓孩子活在什麼社會中
when you think which we want for our kids.
想一想的話，答案其實很簡單
Ms. Suenaga,
末永老師
you sometimes look sad.
妳有時會露出傷心的表情
No, I don't.
沒有啊
Is it hard to forget him?
妳還無法忘記他嗎？
Marrying him wasn't--
不，嫁給他不是…
No.
不是
I don't mean him.
我不是說他
The high school student we saw at the used book store
我說的是在二手書店看到的高中生
wearing the Seitoichi High uniform.
穿著西斗一高的制服
Do you still
妳還在…
care for him?
想著他嗎？
400 years ago, you could still see many stars even in Tokyo.
四百年前，在東京也能看到很多星星
A shooting star.
流星
Hey.
嘿
I'm sorry.
對不起
A friend of a friend teaches at Koboshi Junior High,
我朋友的朋友在子星中學當老師
so I heard what happened.
過去發生了什麼，我都聽說了
I'm not trying to blame you.
我並不是要責怪妳
I hoped I could help in some way.
只是想幫助妳
I'm sorry to have pried.
對不起，擅自打聽妳的過去
If you ever want to talk,
如果妳願意分享心事
I'm here for you.
我隨時都願意傾聽
I just wanted to tell you that.
我只是想告訴妳這些
Three years ago,
三年前
I was supposed to get married.
我本來要結婚
But
但是
I fell for someone else.
我喜歡上了別人
It was him.
那就是他
It's this late already?
已經這麼晚啦
I'll walk you home.
我送妳回去吧
I want to be with you.
我想跟你在一起
What?
什麼？
I don't want to go home.
我不想回去
I want to spend the rest of today with you.
今天我想一直跟你在一起
What's the rush?
妳幹嘛這麼焦急？
More like it's been dragging on for years.
不如說已經拖好幾年了
He was
他是
my student.
我的學生
So I ran away and distanced myself
所以我像逃跑一樣地離開了
to avoid seeing him.
為了避開他
But I remember
但我曾回想起
over and over
好幾次回想起
how he was that day.
那天看到的他
I'm glad he seemed well.
太好了，他看起來過得很好
I'm relieved
他能露出笑容
to see him smiling.
真是太好了
He worked hard, getting into the best school in the area.
他努力考上縣內最好的高中
He's facing forward.
正朝未來前進
That's good to know.
知道他這樣真是太好了
But me,
但是只有我
I'm the only one still where I was,
只有我還在原地踏步
unable to move forward.
無法向前邁進
It's huge!
好大間哦！
Wow, this is crazy.
哇，太誇張了
Hey, the bath is huge!
喂，浴室好大間哦！
Oh, no!
噢，糟糕！
Kuroiwa!
黑岩！
What are you doing?
妳在幹嘛？
It won't turn off!
我關不掉！
I…
我…
I want to see you naked.
我想看你的裸體
Because I like you.
因為我喜歡你，所以我想看
We swam together in junior high.
國中不是在泳池一起游泳嗎？
Not like that.
不是那個意思
It was always just me looking at you.
那時完全是我一廂情願
You were always focused on Suenaga, and I get that.
你總是注視著末永，我都知道
I was a little crazy back then.
我那時腦袋很奇怪
That's how much
我就是那麼地
I loved her.
喜歡她
Ms. Suenaga.
那麼地喜歡著老師
And now?
現在呢？
I'll never see her.
我不能再見她了
She's probably
她大概
already married by now.
已經結婚了
Let's forget.
忘了吧
I'll help you forget.
我來幫你忘記她
You have moved forward.
妳已經前進了
Ms. Suenaga.
末永老師
You're moving forward.
妳已經向前走了
I've watched you.
我一直在旁邊看著
Coming to this school,
妳來到這所學校
talking to all the students,
和每一位同學交流
getting to know everyone.
跟大家相處
You help the other teachers,
幫忙其他老師
gained the parents' trust,
也贏得家長的信賴
and just work hard every day.
妳每天都很努力
Slowly, one step at a time, you're moving forward.
慢慢地、一步步地向著前方前進
You're okay.
很好哦
Thank you.
謝謝你
It's nothing.
哪裡
If…
如果…
If you really…
如果你真的…
I'm sorry.
抱歉
It's okay.
沒關係
-Chief, um-- -Good work today.
-部長，那個… -辛苦了
What? Hey!
幹嘛？喂！
Hey!
喂！
What do you want?
你想怎麼樣？
Not again.
我不想再一次
If you're still
如果你還是
hung up on Hijiri,
想著小聖
and just using me…
只是利用我…
Treating me
當我
like some substitute.
是備胎
I can't take it.
我無法接受
It's okay.
沒關係
Your wife was all crazy.
你太太很歇斯底里
She barged in and yelled at me.
闖進我家亂吼一通
Let's go out next time.
下次約外面見面吧
Ayano?
彩乃？
She's used to being home alone.
她習慣一個人看家了
Anyway,
話說回來
there's an interesting new teacher.
我發現有個很有意思的新老師
I found a good one.
發現好目標了
How?
怎麼了？
I did some research.
我調查過了
After you said she was teaching, I asked around everywhere.
你說她還在當老師，我便到處去打聽
After causing such a scandal, how could she still be teaching?
她引起那麼大的風波 現在居然還在當老師？
Is what she did really forgivable?
她做的事能被寬恕嗎？
I was hoping you could love me.
我希望妳也能喜歡我
Are you okay?
橘同學，妳沒事吧？
Do you see us working out?
我們能順利走下去嗎？
Wanna know where Suenaga is?
你想知道末永在哪裡嗎？
You have a secret, don't you?
妳有不可告人的秘密，是吧？
Subtitle translation by: Zensho Yamamoto
字幕翻譯：楊易